Guide to the John Herzog Collection on Herzog, Heine, Geduld, Inc. MC.289
New York University Archives
John Herzog Collection on Herzog, Heine, Geduld, Inc.
1925, 1947, 1961-2017, undated
New York University Archives
Herzog, John E.
MC.289
36.5 Linear Feet in 7 record cartons, 22 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 5 small flat boxes, 4 oversize flat boxes, and 1 small box
4.79 Gigabytes
John Herzog is a businessman, founder of the Museum of American Finance, and former Chairman and CEO of Herzog, Heine, Geduld, Inc., a financial services company founded by Herzog's family in 1926 and eventually purchased by Merrill Lynch in 2000. This collection contains Herzog, Heine, Geduld, Inc. historial material accumulated by Herzog and used as research for his book on the company's history, A Billion to One. Company files include correspondence, financial statements, reports, index cards on active and inactive trades, as well as 60th and 70th company anniversary material in paper and electronic format. This collection also contains a significant amount of the company's print advertisements dating from the 1970s through 1990s. Herzog's business diary entries and personal correspondence are also found in this collection. Herzog's 1966 Master's thesis, which was a precursor to his book, as well as later book typescripts and the published book itself can also be found in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by John Herzog in May 2018, March 2019, June 2019, and September 2022; the accession numbers associated with these gift are 2018.015, 2019.043, 2019.058, and 2022.093.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
John Herzog is the former Chairman and Chief Executive Officer of Herzog, Heine, Geduld, Inc. as well as the Founder and Chairman Emeritus of the Museum of American Finance. Herzog is also Chairman Emeritus of Spink/Smythe, an auction house specializing in antique stocks and bonds, banknotes, coins, autographs, and photographs. In 2017, his book on the history of Herzog, Heine, Geduld, Inc., A Billion to One, was published. As of 2018, Herzog is a member of the Board of Overseers at the Leonard N. Stern School of Business at New York University.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
The John Herzog Collection on Herzog, Heine, Geduld, Inc. contains 70 years of office files for the New York area investment company Herzog, Heine, Geduld, Inc., including a trader's position book, correspondence, financial statements, index cards on active and inactive trades, reports, tax documents, photographs, meeting minutes, and office floor plans. The majority of office files range in date from the 1920s to the mid-2000s. The 60th and 70th company anniversary material contains paper and electronic files, including invitation lists, planning memos, and dinner table assignments from 1996. Files and reports related to the company's mergers and sales throughout its history can also be found in this collection. A significant number of the company's print advertisements dating from the 1970s through the 1990s can be found in this collection in the form of proofs, samples, and original artwork. A mouse pad and pin with the company logo is included in this collection. John Herzog accumulated and used these office files while writing his 2017 book on the company's history, A Billion to One, which was an expanded version of his 1966 Master's thesis. Other book sources include photocopies and electronic images of Herzog's business diary entries (1964-1977), personal correspondence, and certificates. A typescript and published copy of A Billion to One is also in this collection.
Appraisal
The University Archivist was consulted on 7/27/2018 and decided not to retain a CD-RW containing duplicate digital images of diary entries which existed in analog form in the collection.
Historical Note
The firm of Parmer, Herzog, and Chadwick was established by Robert L. Herzog in 1926 as a bond trading and brokerage company. The New York area company suffered losses in the stock market crash of 1929 but stayed in business by trading in foreign bonds. Over the years, the firm evolved into Herzog, Heine, Geduld, Inc., becoming a member of the New York Stock Exchange, performing retail brokerage, clearing, bond brokerage and limited investment banking and related financial services. The company was acquired by Merrill Lynch in 2000.
Investment banking -- United States.; Financial statements.; Correspondence.; Advertisements; Diaries; Financial services industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Securities industry; Herzog, John E.; Herzog, Heine, Geduld, Inc.; Merrill Lynch & Co. (1973- )
- Trader's Position Book, Office Files, 1926-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1-21)
- Office Files, 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1-19)
- Office Files, 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1-20)
- Office Files, 1979-1985 (Box 4, Folder 1-19)
- Office Files, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1-18)
- Office Files, 1988-1993 (Box 6, Folder 1-19)
- Office Files, 1993-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1-19)
- Office Files, 1996; .0066 Megabytes in 11 documents (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_289_ER_1)
- Office Files and A Billion to One-related, 1973, 1980-2014 (Box 8, Folder 1-19)
- Diary Entries, Master's Thesis, and Office-Related Binders, 1964-1977, 1985, 1999 (Box 9, Item 1-5)
- Office Reference Books, Reports, Index Cards, 1936, 1947, 1985-1996 (Box 10, File 1-10)
- Print Advertisements, 1970s-1990s (Box 11, Box 12, Box 13)
- Office Floor Plans, Print Advertisements, and Herzog Certificates, 1970s-1990s (Box 14, Folder 1-3, Box Shared University Archives 005, Folder 7)